A Guide to the Papers of the Southern Student Organizing Committee 1959-1977
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Southern Student Organizing Committee 1959-1977
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11192-f
This collection consists of ca. 500 items (5 Hollinger boxes, ca. 2 linear feet).
These papers were collected by Bill and Betsy Jean Towe, David and Ronda Kotelchuck, Bruce Smith and Steve Wise.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the University of Virginia Library on June 28, 2000, collectively by Bruce Smith, Woodbridge, Virginia, Steve Wise, Atlanta, Georgia, Bill and Betsy Jean Towe, Cary, North Carolina, and David and Ronda Kotelchuck, New York, New York, through Gregg Michel, Helotes, Texas.
Biographical and Historical Information
The New South Student and materials from the Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee, an interracial group of college students, were donated by Bill and Betsy Jean Towe. The Towes were the senior participants in the Virginia Summer Project held in several counties in Southside Virginia in 1965 and organized and led by the VSCRC. The Virginia Summer project involved anti- segregation protests, voter registration work, and other civil rights activities in this area of historically high black population. It was modeled after the Freedom Summer campaign in Mississippi in 1964.
Other Southern Student Organizing Committee and Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee materials were given by Bruce Smith, a student at Lynchburg College, member of VSCRC, and a participant in the Virginia Summer Project, whose activism, support of black equality, and opposition to the Vietnam War, made him a well-known figure to the school's administration. By 1968, Smith was playing a leading role in the Richmond SSOC chapter.
Southern Student Organizing Committee and Nashville materials were donated by David Kotelchuck, a young Vanderbilt professor, and Ronda Stiley Kotelchuck, active in the Nashville headquarters of the SSOC and participant in the Virginia Summer Project.
Steve Wise has donated materials which supplement his other papers given previously to Special Collections. Wise was a graduate history student at the University of Virginia and the Southern Student Organizing Committee chairman in 1966-1967.
Scope and Content Information
These papers consist of correspondence and miscellaneous publications, some published by other organizations. There are also printed items, memoranda, mimeographed publications, newsletters, newspapers, articles, typed manuscripts, news clippings, order blanks, agendas, conference materials and form letters.
Subjects with individual folders include the founding of the Southern Student Organizing Committee; the Cone Mill Strike at Greensboro, North Carolina; Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee material; the Whiteville Strike against the National Spinning Company, Columbus County, North Carolina; and demonstrations in Nashville, Tennessee and at Vanderbilt University protesting segregation at the Campus Grill and elsewhere.
Contents List
- Appalachian Student Press(West Virginia S.S.O.C.) 1969 Jan-Mar (Box 1)
- Cone Mills Strike 1967 Feb-Jun (Box 1)
- Demonstrations in Nashville and at Vanderbilt University and the Founding of the Southern Student Organizing Committee 1962-1967, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Demonstrations in Nashville and at Vanderbilt University and the Founding of the Southern Student Organizing Committee -- Miscellaneous 1959-1966 (Box 1)
- Freedom Schools in Mississippi 1964 (Box 1)
- Labor Correspondence & Materials 1967 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Literature re: Vietnam, Students for a Democratic Society, Housing Issues, and SNCC 1963-1969 (Box 1)
- News clippings re: Virginia and Civil Rights 1965 Sep-Nov (Box 1)
- Publications by William H. Towe 1965-1972 (Box 1)
- "Southern Consciousness" and "Southern Nationalism" 1967-1969 (Box 1)
- "The Southern Student Organizing Committee" by Ron K. Parker and other papers related to the SSOC's history 1965 Jan 5-1967 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Conferences, Events & Membership Meetings 1964-1969 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Constution, By-Laws, Officers, etc. and Resolution to Dissolve the S.S.O.C. ca. 1964-1969 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Correspondence 1965-1968 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Correspondence from J.W. Stephenson (Steve) Wise, Jr. 1966 Jul-1969 Mar (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Correspondence to J.W. Stephenson (Steve) Wise, Jr. 1965 Nov-1969 May (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Executive Committee and Staff Materials 1964-1969 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Finances 1966-1968 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Handbook 1969 Spring (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Literature Lists ca. 1964-1969 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Civil Rights) 1965 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: the Draft) [post 1963] (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Labor) 1965-1968 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Organizing) 1965-1968 (Box 2)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Politics) n.d. (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Poverty) 1965, n.d. (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Power Structure Research) n.d. (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: the South) 1964-1969 (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: University Reform and Education) n.d. (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Literature (re: Women's Issues) ca. 1968 (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Membership Mailing 1966 Nov-1967 Jun (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. News clippings 19661-969, 1977 (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Newsletters 1964-1968, 6 folders (Box 3)
- S.S.O.C. Newsletters (Arkansas) 1969 Mar-May (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Newsletters (Georgia) 1968 Oct-1969 Feb (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Newsletters (High School "Iceberg!") 1969 Jan-Mar (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Newsletters (North Carolina) ca. 1968 Nov-Dec (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Newsletters (Virginia) 1968-Mar-1969 Apr (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Press Releases 1967 Mar-1968 Mar (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Proposals 1966-1967 (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Prospectus 1967-1969 (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Publicity Handbook n.d. (Box 4)
- S.S.O.C. Worklist Mailing 1966 Mar-1969 Mar (Box 4)
- Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee 1964-1967 (Box 4)
- Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee -- Amelia County Information 1965-1966 (Box 4)
- Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee -- Handbooks for Voter Registration and Education 1965 May-Aug, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee and Lynchburg College 1965-1966 (Box 5)
- Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee -- Southampton Freedom News and the New Virginia 1965-1966, 1969 (Box 5)
- Virginia Students Civil Rights Committee -- Thomas Wansley Trial 1965 Nov, 1967 (Box 5)
- Whiteville Strike at National Spinning Company, Columbus County, North Carolina 1966-1967, n.d., 3 folders (Box 5)
- Whiteville Strike at National Spinning Company, Columbus County, North Carolina -- Material for Report ca. 1967 Jul (Box 5)
- Whiteville Strike at National Spinning Company, Columbus County, North Carolina -- News clippings 1967 Apr 6-Aug 18 (Box 5)